Guide to the Society of American Historians Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Society of American Historians Records,
1879-1976
[Bulk Dates: 1939-1976].
Society of American Historians.
10 linear ft. (24 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1420
6915231
This collection contains the early records of the Society of American Historians (SAH). The bulk of the material relates to the founding of the magazine American Heritage in 1954, and the establishment of the Francis Parkman and the Allan Nevins Prizes, awarded by the SAH since 1957 and 1961, respectively. Also present is a small amount of research material collected by Allan Nevins, Columbia University history professor and one of the founders of the SAH.
Historical Note
The Society of American Historians (SAH) was founded in 1939 by Allan Nevins (1890-1971) and several other historians for the purpose of promoting literary distinction in the writing of history and biography.
Until the mid-1950s, the principal aim of the SAH was in launching a history magazine that could appeal to a wide audience beyond the academic community. Nevins, a history professor at Columbia University and a two-time Pulitzer winner, initially proposed the idea of publishing a popular magazine of history to the American Historial Association (AHA). The AHA declined this proposal, however, which induced Nevins to establish the SAH in 1939 to undertake the publishing project. It took the SAH fifteen years to realize the idea, and over the years tentative titles for the publication included History, Horizons, Living History, and Milestones. In 1954, in cooperation with the American Association for State and Local History, the magazine finally came into being as the American Heritage.
For a brief period from 1952 to 1953, the SAH also ran the History Agency, an organization with the goal of providing the media with the services of professional historians. Although the History Agency was short-lived, one of its products was a collection of scripts for the 1953 radio series Omnibus, which was aired by the National Broadcasting Company.
Since the mid-1950s, the SAH's main focus has been in awarding prizes to promote historical writing with an American theme. In 1957, in order to stimulate the writing of history as literature, the SAH established the annual Francis Parkman Prize to honor the best nonfiction book of the year. The first Parkman Prize was awarded to George F. Kennan, Russia Leaves the War (Princeton University Press). Since 1960, the SAH has also awarded the Allan Nevins Prize, annually, for the best-written doctoral dissertation in history. Most of the winning dissertations have subsequently been published.
Presidents of the SAH have included Douglas Southall Freeman (1939-1944), James P. Baxter III (1944-1946), Allan Nevins (1946-1961), Eric F. Goldman (1961-1969), John A. Garraty (1969-1971) and Barbara Tuchman (1971-1975). After several revisions to its policy, the SAH limited its membership, in the the late 1960s, to invitation only.
Scope and Content
The Society of American Historians Records include material from the first four decades of the SAH. Available in this collection are administrative records such as minutes and membership lists, financial records, correspondence, printed materials, and photographs.
The bulk of the collection concerns the founding of the magazine American Heritage in 1954. Included are minutes, correspondence, fundraising letters, and promotional materials. Aside from the letters among SAH members that discuss the scope of the magazine, fundraising letters comprise the bulk of the correspondence.
Material related to the annual Francis Parkman and the Allan Nevins Prizes also comprises a large part of the collection. Correspondence with history departments regarding submissions for the awards, and with publishers makes up the bulk of the prize material, but guest lists, photos and documents relating to the annual awards dinner are also present.
The collection includes a small amount of Allan Nevins' research material. The research notes and documents concern Nevins' books about the John D. Rockefeller and the Rockefeller family.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series
Series I: Administrative Records, 1939-1975
Series II: Correspondence, 1939-1975
Series III: Magazine Project, 1941-1959
Series IV: History Agency, 1952-1953
Series V: Awards and Special Occasions, 1944-1976
Series VI: Financial Records, 1941-1974
Series VI: Allen Nevins--Personal Research Files, 1879-1886, Undated
Subjects
American Heritage Publishing Company.; Columbia University--Faculty.; National Broadcasting Company.; Rockefeller Foundation.; Baxter, James Phinney,--1893-1975.; Canby, Courtlandt.; Freeman, Douglas Southall,--1886-1953.; Garraty, John A. (John Arthur),--1920-2007.; Goldman, Eric Frederick,--1915-1989.; Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.; Parkman, Francis,--1823-1893.; Tuchman, Barbara Wertheim.; Geographic; Historians--United States.; Historians--United States--Correspondence.; Genre; Occupation
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
The Society of American Historians Gift 1990s
The Society of American Historians Gift 2005
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1939- 1975
  This series includes charters of the SAH, and minutes from annual meetings and council meetings. The minutes are arranged chronologically. Also included are membership lists, correspondence and inquiries regarding membership.
  - Annual Meetings, 1944-1968
    (Missing 1949 and 1959)
    - 1944-1951, (7 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - 1955-1961, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
    - 1966-1968, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Board--Executive, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Council Meetings, 1941-1966
    (Missing 1942,1949,1952, 1962-1963)
    - 1941-1953, (10 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-27)
    - 1957-1966, (8 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-35)
  - Charters, 1939-1960
    - Certificate of Incorporation, 1939, 1960, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Certificate of Resolution, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Constitution--Draft, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Constitution and By-Laws, 1944, 1960, Undated, (4 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
  - Membership, 1939-1975
    - Correspondence
      - Inquiries, 1953-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
      - Invitation, 1939-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Invitation, 1970-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
      - Reorganization, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - List, 1939, 1943-1954, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 2-8)
    - List, 1956-1974, Undated, (9 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1939-1975
  Correspondence among SAH members regarding the general business of the SAH can be found here. The series also includes inquiries from the public regarding the activities of the SAH. Correspondence related to the magazine project was filed separately by the SAH and can be found in Series III: Magazine Project.
  - Boyd, Julian P, 1941-1950 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clemen, Rogers
    - Garraty, John A., 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Krout, John A., 1943-1947 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Nevins, Allan, 1943-1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Counsellors at Law, 1944-1962, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Krout, John A.
    - Freeman, Douglas, 1941-1944 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Nevins, Allan, 1941-1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nevins, Allan, 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Council and Directors, 1939-1974
    - Appointment of Officers, 1939-1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Council, 1961-1967, (7 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 7-13)
    - Directors, 1968-1974, (4 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
  - General, 1943-1959, (9 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 18-26)
  - General, 1960-1975, (11 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-11)
  - Inquiries, 1952-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - Inquiries--regarding Society of American Historians, 1956-1974 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Projects
    - American Heritage, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - American Presidents Project--Reader’s Digest, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Book Plan, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Fellowship, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Newcomen Society, 1944-1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - World of History and the American Story, 1953-1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series III: Magazine Project, 1941-1959
  This series consists of materials related to the founding of the American Heritage magazine. The bulk of the material dates from the late 1940s to the mid-1950s. Included are minutes from magazine committees, correspondence and memorandum among the SAH members. This series also contains numerous fundraising letters sent to various individuals and organizations. Lists and clippings regarding prospective donors, and progress reports sent to the contributors can also be found here. Letters to and from Courtland Canby, who was in charge of the financial campaign, comprise the bulk of the correspondence, which is arranged alphabetically.
  This series also contains materials relating to a 1951-1952 survey on the use of history in the mass media. The SAH presented its findings at a conference in 1952, and along with papers and speeches, research materials such as clippings, articles, and questionnaires are available. Correspondence with the Rockefeller Foundation, which funded the survey, is here as well.
  Advertisements, pamphlets, prospectuses and other promotional material are included in this series.
  - Committee Minutes
    - Continuing and Advisory, 1944-1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Finance, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Joint, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Liaison, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Magazine, 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Steering, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1941-1959
    - General, 1948-1954, (6 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 13-18)
    - American Heritage--Joint Sponsorship, 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Burlingame, Roger
      - General, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Canby, Henry, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Clemen, Rudolf, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Pringle, Henry, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Canby, Courtland
      - General, 1949-1951, (8 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 4-11)
      - General, 1950-1953, Undated, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
      - Applicants, 1948-1952 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Authors--Potential, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Burlingame, Roger, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Canby, Henry, 1949-1952 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Clemen, Rudolf, 1948-1953, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
      - D-F, 1949-1950, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 11-14)
      - K, 1949-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
      - Keener, Ruth, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - L, 1949-1951 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Library of Congress--Copyright, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - M, 1949-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
      - Nevins, Allan, 1950-1954 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Pringle, Henry, 1949-1951 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - R-W, 1950-1951, (7 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 10-16)
      - Wecter, Dixon, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Y-Z, 1949-1951 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Canby, Henry
      - General, 1949-1954 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Clemen, Rudolf, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Pringle, Henry, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Nevins, Allan, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Clemen, Rudolf
      - General, 1947-1952 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Gross, Nancy, 1950-1954 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Nevins, Allan, 1943-1955, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Gross, Nancy, 1950-1953 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - History Publisher’s Foundation, 1943-1953 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Krout, John A., 1941-1943 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Nevins, Allan, 1944-1952 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Pringle, Henry, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Richardson Wood and Co., 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Subscription Queries, 1942-1951 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising, 1944-1953
    - Donors--Prospective
      - General--List--Index Cards, 1950 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - General--List, 1949-1952, (3 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 15-17)
      - Foundations
        - General, 1944-1950 (Box 11, Folder 18)
        - Ford Foundation, 1948-1953 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Labor Union, 1948-1950 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Founders
      - Budget Proposal, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - List, 1948-1950 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Pledges
        - Original and Extension, 1950-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
        - Release of, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Stock Proposal, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Dinners and Luncheons
      - Boston, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - California, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Chicago, 1950 and 1952 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Denver, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - New York, 1949-1950, (3 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 13-15)
      - Philadelphia, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - St. Louis, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Texas, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - Union League, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - Washington, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Subscribers--Index Cards, 1951 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - History in the Mass Media, 1941-1953
    - Correspondence--Rockefeller Foundation, 1941-1953, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Conference, 1952, (4 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 3-6)
    - Survey
      - General, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Periodicals, Radio, and Televisions, 1951-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
      - Periodicals, Radio, and Television, 1951-1952 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Television and Film, 1951-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Promotional, 1941-1952
    - History
      - Advertisement-- New York Times Book Review, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Direct Mail, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Dummy Copy, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Letters from Readers, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Prospectus, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Horizons
      - Prospectus, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - “Widening Our Horizons in Time and Space,” 1944 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - “What Makes History Readable,” 1944 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Living History
      - “A Monthly Magazine”--Henry Seidel Canby, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Comments--From Members, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - “Plan for Experimental Production”--For Henry Luce, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Milestones
      - Comments, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Prospectus, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Table of Contents, circa 1949 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Nevins, Allen
      - Folkways, Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Historical Quiz, Undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Letters to Editors, Undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - News and Backgrounds, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Popular Misconceptions, Undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Reprints, Undated (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - Words, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Projected Articles, late 1940s-early 1950s (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Projected Articles, late 1940s-early 1950s, (4 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
    - Report and News Release, 1941-1952 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Sample of Direct Mails--Other Magazines, 1950s (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Series IV: History Agency, 1952-1953
  This series contains materials related to the History Agency, an organization that from 1952-1953 attempted to connect professional historians with members of the media in need of history services. In addition to correspondence and prospectuses, the series contains radio scripts that the agency prepared for the National Broadcasting Company's series, Omnibus, in 1953.
  - Correspondence--Fundraising, 1952-1953, (2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Omnibus, NBC Radio Scripts
    - “Letters of Mozart,” 1953 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - “Napoleon,” 1953 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - “Roger Williams and the Tradition of Civil Liberties,” 1953 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - “Stroke of Fate,” 1953 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Prospectus, 1952-1953 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - “World of History and the American Story,” 1953-1957 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Series V: Awards and Special Occasions, 1944-1976
  Correspondence, printed material and photographs related to awards and ceremonies constitute this series. The bulk of the material relates to the annual Allan Nevins Prize and the Francis Parkman Prize, and includes, primarily, submission letters from history departments and from publishers. Correspondence regarding the founding of the prizes, guest lists, photos, and reprints of speeches can also be found here.
  - Allan Nevins Prize
    - List of Winners, 1960-1973 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - 1960 Prize-1964 Prize, 1957-1965, (4 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 17-20)
    - 1965 Prize-1974 Prize, 1965-1975, (10 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1-10)
  - Francis Parkman Prize
    - List of Winners, 1956-1973 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - 1955-1959, (5 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 2-6)
    - 1959-1967, (9 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1-9)
    - 1967-1975, (8 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1-8)
    - Mock Certificate, Undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Scribner Prize, 1944-1945 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Special Occasions, 1957-1976
    - Allan Nevins Testimonial Dinner, 1957-1958 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Annual Awards Dinner, 1966-1968, (3 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 11-13)
    - Annual Awards Dinner, 1969-1976, (8 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1-8)
    - St. Louis Breakfast, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Financial Records, 1941-1974
  This series contains annual financial statements and tax records. Financial records relating to the magazine project can be found both in this series and in Series III: Magazine Project.
  - General, 1950-1970 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - American Heritage Magazine, 1957-1966 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Magazine Account, 1948-1952 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Account Book, 1951-1954 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1954 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - General Account--Reports, 1941-1961 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - General Account--Statements and Notes, 1957-1974 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Tax Exemption, 1953- 1973 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Tax Returns, 1967-1974 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Royalties, 1956-1972 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Allan Nevins--Personal Research Files, 1879-1886, Undated
  A small collection of Allen Nevins’ research files, which include original documents, a box of index cards and handwritten research notes on the Rockefellers, make up this series.
  - American States during and after the Revolution--Books and Articles on--Index Cards, Undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller Records
    - Folder Notes 2-29--1875-1885 Undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Folder Notes 31-69--1886-1915 Undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Letter Book Notes--1877-1882 Undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Originals--1879-1886 Undated, (4 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 6-9)